chain_hash: mtf_auD4sSu2NLF0tiaMYFNu_bk
<chain>
<existing_artifact>
[//]: # (code-from-spec: SPEC/domain/code-from-spec/manifest@46H21Guh5w3hIRodQFTqKTnBR_A)

# Manifest format

## Header

The first line of the manifest identifies the framework and version:

```
code-from-spec: v5
```

## Entry

Each subsequent line is one artifact entry. Fields are in fixed order, separated by `;`:

```
ARTIFACT/payments/fees/calculation;path:internal/fees/calculation.go;checksum:Kx9mP2vB7wY2tHsJ8dFak4Xz9pQ;chain:Jz3qR7nL5cW1gT4yK8mDfAx0vBe
```

Fields:
1. `ARTIFACT/<name>` — logical name
2. `path:<path>` — output file path, relative to project root
3. `checksum:<hash>` — hash of file content at generation time
4. `chain:<hash>` — chain hash at generation time
</existing_artifact>
<constraints>
</constraints>
<instructions>
Extract exactly the following from the input:

1. The header line format (with example).
2. The entry line format — fields, separators, ordering
   (with example).

Nothing else.

Place all content under a single `# Manifest format`
heading.

The output will be used as minimal context to teach an
AI agent how to parse and write the manifest file.
Keep it concise.
</instructions>
<input>
# Manifest

The manifest tracks the state of every generated artifact.

This document assumes familiarity with
[CODE_FROM_SPEC.md](../CODE_FROM_SPEC.md).

---

## Location

The manifest is a single file at
`code-from-spec/.manifest`. It is committed to version
control.

If the manifest is lost, it can be regenerated, but the
record of which chain hash produced each artifact is lost.
All artifacts are treated as stale and must be regenerated.

---

## Format

One line per artifact, terminated by a newline (LF).
Entries are ordered alphabetically by logical name.

```
code-from-spec: v5
ARTIFACT/payments/fees/calculation;path:internal/fees/calculation.go;checksum:Kx9mP2vB7wY2tHsJ8dFak4Xz9pQ;chain:Jz3qR7nL5cW1gT4yK8mDfAx0vBe
```

The first line identifies the framework and version.
Subsequent lines are artifact entries.

Each line has four fields in fixed order, separated by
`;`:

- **`ARTIFACT/<name>`** — the logical name of the
  artifact.
- **`path:<path>`** — the output file path, relative to
  the project root.
- **`checksum:<hash>`** — hash of the file content at
  the time of generation.
- **`chain:<hash>`** — the chain hash at the time of
  generation.

All hashes use the same algorithm and encoding defined
in CHAIN_HASH.md (SHA-1, base64url, 27 characters).

---

## Artifact status

The `validate_specs` tool reports the status of each
artifact. Five states exist:

### Up-to-date

The chain hash in the manifest matches the current chain
hash of the node, and the checksum in the manifest matches
the hash of the file on disk.

### Stale

The chain hash in the manifest does not match the current
chain hash of the node. The specification has changed since
the artifact was last generated. The artifact must be
regenerated.

### Modified

The checksum in the manifest does not match the hash of
the file on disk. The file was modified outside of the
framework. An artifact can be both stale and modified.

### Missing

The artifact file does not exist on disk.

### Orphan

The manifest contains an entry whose logical name does not
correspond to any existing node in the spec tree. The node
was deleted or renamed, but the artifact and manifest entry
remain.

---

## Concurrency

The manifest may be read and written concurrently during
artifact generation. Any process that reads the manifest
must acquire a shared lock; any process that writes it
must acquire an exclusive lock. A read must not see a
partially-written manifest, and two writes must not
interleave.
</input>
</chain>
